Finding Aid for the Livingston Gearhart Collection of Photographs, 1896-1969
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Livingston Gearhart Collection of Photographs, 1896-1969
Mus. Arc. 23.3
Gearhart, Livingston
1 box ( 192 photographs )
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains 192 photographs from the personal collection of composer, arranger, and pianist, Livingston Gearhart. They include photographs of Nadia Boulanger and her summer class of 1938 at the Conservatoire Américain de Fontainebleau, Gearhart and his first wife and duo-piano partner, Virginia Morley, Darius Milhaud and his family, and the Budapest String Quartet. The collection also includes four photographs of composer Johannes Brahms in 1896.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Livingston Gearhart. Additional photographs given by the family of Livingston Gearhart in 2012 and again in 2014.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
Entire collection digitized and available in University at Buffalo Libraries Digital Collections.
Biographical Note
Livingston Gearhart was born in Buffalo, New York December 31, 1916. His mother was Lillian Hawley Gearhart, a pianist who had studied for a year under Theodor Leschetizky in Vienna. As a child Gearhart studied piano, oboe, violoncello, and sang in church choirs in Buffalo and New York City. He graduated from high school in East Orange, New Jersey in 1935. He entered Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia in 1935 as an oboe student of Marcel Tabuteau. In his second year he switched his major to study composition with Rosario Scalero and piano with Nadia Reisenberg.
Gearhart sailed to Paris aboard the Normandie in 1937. With generous support from a wealthy American expatriate, he was able to enroll at the Conservatoire Américain de Fontainebleau where he studied music theory and composition with Nadia Boulanger. He was awarded the school's 2nd prize (no first prize was awarded that year) in the Prix Stovall composition competition in 1937. While in Paris he also met Igor Stravinsky, Darius Milhaud, Robert Casadesus, pianist Isodor Philipp, and his future wife and duo-piano partner, Virginia Clotfelter. He and Virginia performed their debut in Paris February 1, 1939 at the Salle Chopin. They received good reviews and were then able to give concerts in other French and Swiss locations until the conditions of World War II caused them to return to the United States.
Virginia Clotfelter adopted the professional name Morley and married Gearhart February 28, 1940 in New York City. They worked at numerous venues, including the Hotel Brevoort and the club, Ruban Bleu, both operated by Herbert Jacoby. The pair spent the summers of 1942 and 1943 as Artists-in-Residence at Morley's alma mater, Mills College in Oakland, California. While there Gearhart was able to study composition with Darius Milhaud. The Budapest String Quartet was also in residence at Mills College during those years and Gearhart and Morley formed friendships with quartet members Alexander and Mischa Schneider. The Morley Gearhart duo was very successful, performing works by Milhaud, Norman Dello Joio, David Diamond, and Stravinsky's Concerto per due pianoforte soli.
The duo received contracts with Columbia Concerts and the Fred Waring Show that extended from 1943-1954. During 1941 to 1954, the two-piano team of Morley and Gearhart performed over 2000 concerts throughout the US and Canada in addition to recording for Columbia Masterworks and Decca Records. Among the many concert dates, the duo performed at the White House for President Dwight D. Eisenhower in 1953. During this period Gearhart also worked as a staff arranger for the Fred Waring Show.
A two-CD retrospective released in 2001, Morley and Gearhart Rediscovered by Ivory Classics, features 22 of Gearhart's two-piano arrangements. Some of these arrangements survive at Penn State in their collection, Fred Waring's America. In many cases Gearhart never fully wrote out his part of a duo so no written arrangement survives.
Livingston Gearhart's output contains several collections written for pedagogical purposes. The first of Gearhart's these works to be published was Clarinet Sessions in 1945. That was followed by similar collections for trumpet, violin, flute, and duos. Gearhart's entire compositional and arranging output includes 400-500 works (counting individual works within the collections).
Gearhart returned to Buffalo in 1955 and was appointed to the faculty of the music department at the University of Buffalo. After a divorce from Virginia Morley, he married violinist and conductor Pamela Gerhart (not a misspelling) in 1955. He taught various courses in keyboard, theory, and orchestration until his retirement in 1985.
Livingston Gearhart had four children: Paul, born to Virginia Morley Gearhart; Kim, Martha, and Fritz, born to Pamela Gearhart. Gearhart died in Buffalo at the age of 79 on July 14, 1996.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 192 photographs from the personal collection of composer, arranger, and pianist, Livingston Gearhart. Many of the photographs include annotations on versos. Some of these were done contemporaneously and others were added at a later time. The photographs include images of Gearhart's early family life, his time in Paris and elsewhere in Europe between 1937 and 1939, Nadia Boulanger and her summer class of 1938 at the Conservatoire Américain de Fontainebleau, Gearhart and his first wife and duo-piano partner, Virginia Morley, Gearhart and Morley at Mills College in California, with composer Darius Milhaud and his family, and the Budapest String Quartet. The collection also includes photographs of oboist Marcel Tabuteau, conductor Walter Damrosch, and bandleader, Fred Waring. A unique component of the collection is the group of four photographs of composer Johannes Brahms taken while he was visiting friends in Krefeld, Germany the weekend after Clara Schumann's funeral in May 1896. An additional folder of twenty-one photocopies of photographs, chiefly of Gearhart and Morley, is included but not described due to the quality of the photocopies.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in three series:
I. Original receipts
II. Additional receipts (2012)
III. Additional receipts (2014)
Container List
- Original receipts, 1896-1948, I.; Items 1-26
  Arranged by size of the print and grouped by subject.
  - Livingston Gearhart and unidentified male onboard the ship, The Normandie, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg001)
    City: Unknown
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting outdoors, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg002)
    City: Paris (France)
  - Livingston Gearhart and group of Nadia Boulanger students sitting at an outdoor café. Virginia Morley is seated across from Gearhart, Nadia Boulanger visible at end of table, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Restaurant 'A la petite chaise' just across from Virginia's. We learned on authority other night that her house is almost 400 yrs old, and in all the guide books or you know what I mean" (Box 1, Item lg003)
  - Livingston Gearhart walking across a street in Paris, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg004)
  - Livingston Gearhart, Virginia Morley, Benjamin Baldwin, Fred Werle (far right), and unidentified male, in the dining pavilion at the Conservatoire Américain de Fontainebleau, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg005)
  - Livingston Gearhart standing on a bridge in Paris, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg006)
  - Livingston Gearhart on board the Normandie, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Possibly earlier than 1938 (Box 1, Item lg007)
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting next to Nadia Boulanger at an outdoor café in Paris, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Boulanger talking to Emma" (Box 1, Item lg008)
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting next to Nadia Boulanger at an outdoor café in Paris, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg009)
  - Nadia Boulanger with her group of singers and others. Livingston Gearhart in the back row, head turned, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "With her group of singers and other people" (Box 1, Item lg010)
  - Nadia Boulanger standing next to a car, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Please save and perhaps return the ones of Boulanger. This is so characteristic - last lesson next week - before the fall, that is. (Box 1, Item lg011)
  - Nadia Boulanger standing with conductor Walter Damrosch in the garden of the restaurant at the American Conservatory, Fontainebleau, July 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified See p.281 in Nadia Boulanger: A Life in Music (Box 1, Item lg012)
  - Nadia Boulanger portrait photograph, undated, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Esparcieux, G. (Box 1, Item lg013)
  - Nadia Boulanger (at piano) with her class of summer 1938, 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Students, including Herve Armington (far left in chair), Ethel Thurston (behind and to left of Boulanger), Louise Talma (behind and right of Boulanger), Livingston Gearhart (behind Talma, to right), and Virginia Morley (seated far right) (Box 1, Item lg014)
  - Marcel Tabuteau standing outside the Drake Hotel in Philadelphia, 1935, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Tabuteau was oboist with Philadelphia Orchestra and taught at Curtis Institute of Music (Box 1, Item lg015)
    City: Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - Livingston Gearhart, Fred Waring, and Virginia Morley at the Gearhart's farm in Pennsylvania, 1948?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg016)
  - Livingston Gearhart and Virginia Morley at Mills College, 1941, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg017)
    City: Oakland (Calif.)
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting on couch with Herve Armington in Igor Stravinsky's parlor, 1938?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg018)
  - Livingston Gearhart walking across street in Paris, circa 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg019)
  - Livingston Gearhart and Virginia Morley with Daniel, Madeleine, and Darius Milhaud, at Mills College, 1941, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg020)
  - Madeleine, Daniel, and Darius Milhaud, 1941, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg021)
  - Budapest String Quartet members with koala bears at Mills College: Josef Roismann, Boris Kroyt, Alexander Schneider, and Mischa Schneider, 1940, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg022)
  - Johannes Brahms tending to a bird dropping on the jacket of Alwin von Beckerath, as Karl Piening, Bram Eldering, Rudolf von der Leyen, and Gustav Ophüls stand nearby, 1896, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Beckerath, Heinz von, 1876-1940 From a group of photographs taken at a gathering of Brahms and his friends in May 1896 following the funeral of Clara Schumann at the Weyermann estate, Hagerhof, in Krefeld, Germany. (Box 1, Item lg023)
    City: Bad Honnef (Germany)
  - Johannes Brahms with Alwin von Beckerath, Gustav Ophüls, and Bram Eldering in Bad Honnef, 1896, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Beckerath, Heinz von, 1876-1940 From a group of photographs taken at a gathering of Brahms and his friends in May 1896 following the funeral of Clara Schumann at the Weyermann estate, Hagerhof, in Krefeld, Germany. (Box 1, Item lg024)
  - Johannes Brahms with Alwin von Beckerath, Gustav Ophüls, and Bram Eldering walking down a path in Bad Honnef, 1896, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Beckerath, Heinz von, 1876-1940 From a group of photographs taken at a gathering of Brahms and his friends in May 1896 following the funeral of Clara Schumann at the Weyermann estate, Hagerhof, in Krefeld, Germany. (Box 1, Item lg025)
  - Johannes Brahms with Emmie Weyermann, wife of Walther Weyermann, at the Weyermann estate, Hagerhof, in Bad Honnef, 1896, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Beckerath, Heinz von, 1876-1940 From a group of photographs taken at a gathering of Brahms and his friends in May 1896 following the funeral of Clara Schumann at the Weyermann estate, Hagerhof, in Krefeld, Germany. (Box 1, Item lg026)
- Additional receipts (2012), circa 1902-1983, II.; Items 26-110
  Arranged in rough chronological order within geographical locations.
  - Livingston Gearhart in suit and tie standing with gazebo in background, circa 1929, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "8th grade graduation E. Orange" (Box 1, Item lg027)
    City: East Orange (N.J.)
  - Livingston Gearhart in suit and tie sitting on porch of house, circa 1929, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "? Grove St. East Orange?" (Box 1, Item lg028)
  - Livingston Gearhart in suit and tie standing in front of house, circa 1929, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "8th grade graduation E. Orange" (Box 1, Item lg029)
  - Livingston Gearhart in vest and tie standing in front of a garage, circa 1929, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Maybe East Orange?" (Box 1, Item lg030)
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting beneath an umbrella with his mother Lillian, circa 1935, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg031)
    City: Orange (N.J.)
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting beneath an umbrella with his sister, Martha Gearhart, circa 1935, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Livingston & me" (Box 1, Item lg032)
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting beneath an umbrella with his sister, Martha Gearhart, circa 1935, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Martha and Livingston, chez Burnett? (Orange, N.J.) 1935? (Box 1, Item lg033)
  - Livingston Gearhart walking beside his sister Martha, circa 1935, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg034)
  - Livingston Gearhart with his sister Martha and unidentified person looking down into what is possibly a fish pond, circa 1935, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg035)
  - Livingston Gearhart at Camp Aldercliff, Weymouth, Nova Scotia, circa 1932, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Weymouth, N.S." (Box 1, Item lg036)
    City: Weymouth (N.S.)
  - Two unidentified males at Camp Aldercliff, Weymouth, Nova Scotia, circa 1932, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Camp Aldercliff, Nova Scotia (Weymouth)" (Box 1, Item lg037)
  - Livingston Gearhart standing and unidentified male laying on ground at Camp Aldercliff, Weymouth, Nova Scotia, circa 1932, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Nova Scotia, Camp Aldercliff, ca. 16" (Box 1, Item lg038)
  - Livingston Gearhart with Sonia and Ethel Gechtoff before portrait of J. Edgar Hoover by Leonid Gechtoff, 1936, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Winter 1936, Phila. Sonia, Mrs. Gechtoff. The portrait is Leonid Gechtoff's rendition of J. Edgar Hoover" (Box 1, Item lg039)
  - View towards water from onboard a ship, probably the U.S.S. Normandie, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Probably the Normandie, aft" (Box 1, Item lg040)
  - View of ships on the ocean at the Port of Southampton, England, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Part of the British fleet coming into Southampton (the first view I had of Europe) (Box 1, Item lg041)
    City: Southampton (England)
  - View of the Serpentine Lake in Hyde Park, London, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "The Serpentine, Hyde Park (London)" (Box 1, Item lg042)
    City: London (England)
  - View of crowd in Hyde Park, London, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Oratory, Hyde Park, London" (Box 1, Item lg043)
  - View of moors in unidentified location, probably England, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "The 'moors'. In the picture, looks like almost anyplace, I know. Characteristic features - such as a line of poplars on the far side, don't show up" (Box 1, Item lg044)
  - Nadia Boulanger behind piano onstage at rehearsal with London Philharmonic Orchestra, 1937, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Rehearsal London Philharmonic taken from the organ loft where I was turning pages. Boulanger is in the center behind the piano" (Box 1, Item lg045)
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting on top of wall in Paris, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Call this one Innocent abroad" (Box 1, Item lg046)
  - Livingston Gearhart standing in front of a Café Bar Restaurant, presumably in Paris, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item lg047)
  - Two unidentified males in white jackets standing at end of reflecting pool, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Getting interested in 'trick' shots - you know, artistic photography" (Box 1, Item lg048)
  - Livingston Gearhart standing near the Arc de triomphe, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Arc de Triomphe on way to Valery's to hear Schnabel records. Note tandem bicycle." (Box 1, Item lg049)
  - Livingston Gearhart standing before the main doors at Chartres Cathedral, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Probably Notre Dame [crossed out] Chartres." (Box 1, Item lg050)
    City: Chartres (France)
  - Livingston Gearhart looking over a balcony in Paris, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Paris with a slight affectation" (Box 1, Item lg051)
  - Livingston Gearhart standing beneath Paul-Eugène Benet statue of Jean Vauquelin at the Château-Musée de Dieppe, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Chateau at Dieppe. I am beneath the statue. Chez Mme. Forget" (Box 1, Item lg052)
    City: Dieppe (France)
  - Wall mask fountain at Fontainebleau, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Fountain in the courtyard at Fontainebleau" (Box 1, Item lg053)
    City: Fontainebleau (France)
  - Carp pond at Fontainebleau, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Carp pond near the palace (Fontainebleau) (Box 1, Item lg054)
  - Courtyard at Fontainebleau, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Another courtyard" (Box 1, Item lg055)
  - Livingston Gearhart in front of building at Fontainebleau, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Windows upper right are mine. Fontainebleau, Summer 1937" (Box 1, Item lg056)
  - Palace of Fontainebleau, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "More of the chateau" (Box 1, Item lg057)
  - Livingston Gearhart standing on the Le Ponts des Arts bridge in Paris with the Louvre in the background, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Le pont des Arts. Louvre in the background (Box 1, Item lg058)
  - Chateau Daumesnil?, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Chateau Daumesnil (of the Valery's) - not a good picture" (Box 1, Item lg059)
  - Cathedral of Notre Dame, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Notre Dame from the derrierre" (Box 1, Item lg060)
  - Livingston Gearhart searching through second hand music at bookstalls along the Seine, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Second hand music on the Seine. The urge to browse is irresistable" (Box 1, Item lg061)
  - Livingston Gearhart searching through second hand music at bookstalls along the Seine, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Can I get you anything at the bookstalls? Tell me the kinds of things you want." (Box 1, Item lg062)
  - Hallway inside the American Conservatory at Fontainebleau, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Another hall in the conservatoire - my studio is a door on the left" (Box 1, Item lg063)
  - Hallway inside the American Conservatory at Fontainebleau, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Corridor in the Conservatoire" (Box 1, Item lg064)
  - Livingston Gearhart sitting on bench with unidentified male, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Rue Grand (Main Street) Fontainebleau" (Box 1, Item lg065)
  - View of an alleyway between buildings, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "It was all a mistake setting so much stone in. Houses on this street date back to 1400. My most beautiful views are yet to come. Have bought you long white gloves. (Box 1, Item lg066)
  - Palace of Fontainebleau and its gardens, 1937?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Dans les jardins du palais (Fontainebleau)" (Box 1, Item lg067)
  - Walter Damrosch and Nadia Boulanger at Fontainebleau, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Damrosch at Fontainebleau" (Box 1, Item lg068)
  - Nadia Boulanger and M. Hufstadter at Fontainebleau, 1937, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Mme Boulanger et M. Hufstadter (1937 or 8)" (Box 1, Item lg069)
  - Nadia Boulanger and her Fontainebleau class of 1938 (clipping), 1938, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Esparcieux, G. Clipped from magazine or journal (Box 1, Item lg070)
  - View from Igor Stravinsky's Paris apartment window, 1938?, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "View from Stravinsky's apartment" (Box 1, Item lg071)
  - View of road beneath trees in Gargenville (location of Nadia Boulanger's summer home), 1939, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "Allee d'Hannecourt - exposed too long, but I send it anyway. The house Boulanger lent to me in the country." (Box 1, Item lg072)
    City: Gargenville (France)
  - Livingston Gearhart with unidentified woman standing at a well at the maison dite de l'enfer, Chatillon-Coligny, 1939, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified Note on verso: "At the well with Valentine. Summer of 1939 at 'L'Enfer', Chatillon-Coligny (Box 1, Item lg073)
    City: Châtillon-Coligny (France)